<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">

<title><trademark>InfiniSQL</trademark> Frequently Asked Questions</title>
<info><pubdate><?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d H:M:S"?></pubdate>
<productname>InfiniSQL</productname><productnumber>0.1.2-alpha</productnumber></info>

<qandaset defaultlabel="qanda">

  <qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
Is InfiniSQL based upon or derived from another similar product?
  </para>
</question>
<answer>
<para>
No. InfiniSQL is written from scratch, primarily in C++, with some
Python. Over 30,000 lines of code. There are a few symbol
definitions imported from the PostgreSQL project which are necessary to
use the PostgreSQL Frontend/Backend Protocol. This allows any PostgreSQL
client to communicate with InfiniSQL. InfiniSQL is a completely independent,
"greenfield" RDBMS system.
</para>
</answer>
  </qandaentry>
<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
How does InfiniSQL compare to Hadoop? Why not just put an SQL
interface on top of Hadoop to get a scalable RDBMS?
    </para>
  </question>
<answer>
  <para>
    InfiniSQL and Hadoop excel in different capacities. Hadoop is geared
for analysis of data occurring after the events occur.
 InfiniSQL, on the other hand, provides
very high throughput for queries happening in real time, as events occur.
In a way, InfiniSQL and Hadoop can complement one another, just as
legacy environments split duties between online transaction processing (OLTP)
and data warehousing. InfiniSQL is not designed for the same types of analytics queries at which Hadoop excels.
And Hadoop-based systems do not support the transaction
processing throughput of InfiniSQL. The reason to put a SQL interface on
top of Hadoop is mainly to standardize the way to query the data. It does
not turn Hadoop into an extreme scale transaction processing system. InfiniSQL
is for extreme scale transaction processing and real time data collection.
  </para>
<para>
  Internally, InfiniSQL and Hadoop may have some similarities.
InfiniSQL uses a form of map and reduce. It coordinates activities
across multiple nodes to manipulate data for each transaction.
If InfiniSQL had columnar storage (in addition to its existing row-based), then
it might behave analogously to Hadoop. The design goals for each platform
are very similar--to provide massive scalability for database activities
spread across commodity compute and storage resources.
</para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>
<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
      Is InfiniSQL Open Source?
    </para>
  </question>
<answer>
  <para>
    Yes! Get it here: <link xl:href="https://github.com/infinisql/infinisql">https://github.com/infinisql/infinisql</link>. InfiniSQL is primarily released
under the <link xl:href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/agpl-3.0.html">AGPL</link>, with the main exception being the API and library for
creating stored procedures, which are under the <link xl:href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl.html">LGPL</link>. All code is
owned by Mark Travis. An alternative commercial license is available for
customers who do not wish to comply with the open source license terms.
Send inquiries to <email>info@infinisql.org</email>.
  </para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>
<qandaentry>
<question>
  <para>
    How far can InfiniSQL scale?
  </para>
</question>
<answer>
  <para>
    This is unknown. InfiniSQL has been <link xl:href="/blog/2013/1112/benchmarking-infinisql">benchmarked</link> to run on 12 x
4-core x64_64-based servers. But the limit on servers was budgetary, and
not because of a limitation in InfiniSQL. InfiniSQL is an open source
project which is not part of some institution, so all costs, such
as those for benchmarking hardware, are borne out of pocket. But
based on InfiniSQL's actor-based architecture, and the promising benchmark
performance, InfiniSQL should scale to a very large number of nodes.
On the 12 node benchmark, over 500,000 multi-node transactions were performed
per second by over 100,000 simultaneous client connections. The InfiniSQL team will gladly assist anybody who wishes in earnest to perform
benchmarks of their own. Tools that are used to benchmark InfiniSQL are
included with the source code, and a <link xl:href="/docs/guide/">guide</link> to benchmarking using those tools is available.
  </para>
</answer>  
</qandaentry>
<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
      Why not work on enhancing another open source RDBMS to make it scalable? Isn't InfiniSQL a duplication of effort?
    </para>
  </question>
<answer>
  <para>
    Scalability limitations of existing open source databases, such as
PostgreSQL and MySQL, are a function of their design, which in turn is
pretty common to nearly all RDBMS platforms going back decades. This design
assumes a single server host which tightly couples processing logic, cache
and storage. There are some enhanced legacy RDBMS products which are able
to horizontally scale some types of workloads. But those are extensive
modifications of the base product. InfiniSQL's internals are quite
radically different than PostgreSQL and MySQL. At inception, it made more sense to
start with a fresh project rather than to re-shape an existing one.
  </para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>
<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
      What are "complex, multi-node transactions" and why do they matter?
    </para>
  </question>
<answer>
  <para>
    InfiniSQL excels at performing this type of transaction. They comprise
transactions that have records on at least 2 hosts. A simple example is
a transfer between a buyer and a seller in an application where any
buyer can purchase from any seller. For any transaction of this type, 
those two account records would very likely be spread on different hosts because there is no way to force all possible buyer-seller pairs to be on the same
host (unless you have just one big server, just like a legacy RDBMS). This
type of workload generates a lot of traffic for every single transaction.
InfiniSQL provides head and shoulders better performance for this type of
workload than any other distributed database product, whether of the NewSQL
variety, or a clustered legacy RDBMS.
  </para>
<para>
Without InfiniSQL, workloads like this which need to scale beyond a single
server host, need to be redesigned to support the limitations of the
distributed solution. It's mainly why mainframes and big UNIX servers still exist--the applications on which they run just can't perform well on existing distributed platforms--but InfiniSQL breaks that mold.
</para>
<para>
  InfiniSQL is a great solution even for workloads which don't rely heavily
 on this type of transaction. Think of it this way: since InfiniSQL performs
complex transactions at a very high rate, it also can perform simpler
operations at a high rate. InfiniSQL is designed to perform
all types of operational workloads within a single cluster.
</para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>
<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
Is InfiniSQL only fast because it's in memory?      
    </para>
  </question>
<answer>
  <para>
    Being in memory helps performance a lot. But that's not the reason for
such scalability across multiple nodes, or handling of so many concurrent
connections. There's a section of the
<link xl:href="/docs/overview/">Overview</link> describing future directions
for data storage. InfiniSQL scales and supports massive concurrency because
of it's actor-based core. As additional storage types and interfaces are added,
InfiniSQL will still scale massively--but if the additional components, such
as storage, are slower, InfiniSQL will also necessarily slow down in some
respects.
  </para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>
<qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para>
    When will InfiniSQL be production ready?  
    </para>
  </question>
<answer>
  <para>
    This is unknown. InfiniSQL needs developers, early adopters,
and funding, to come to fruition.
  </para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>

</qandaset>

</article>
